Guide to the World Affairs Council (Gulf Coast/Houston) Records
University of Houston Libraries
World Affairs Council (Gulf Coast/Houston) Records
1976-1998
2010-015
World Affairs Council (Gulf Coast/Houston); Cunningham, William J.; Handy, Robert T.
9.00 Linear Feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
Collection includes records relating to the formation and development of the Gulf Coast Council on Foreign Affairs and its successor organizations, the Gulf Coast World Affairs Council, and the Houston World Affairs Council.
Historical Note:
World Affairs Council (Gulf Coast/Houston) Records collection consists of documents relating to the Gulf Coast Council on Foreign Affairs, Gulf Coast World Affairs Council, and Houston World Affairs Council. In 1976, fourteen individuals founded Gulf Coast Council on Foreign Affairs as a result of their participation in College of the Mainland’s annual, eight-week Great Decisions foreign policy study-discussion program. Organization by-laws designed an organization that was self-sustaining through membership dues and fundraising.
Programs developed by the evolving organization encouraged public awareness of global conditions involving international political, economic, and military issues and introduced participants to the diversity of cultures around the world. It was the Council’s policy to provide information without assuming particular positions, operating from the premise that every citizen in a democratic society has the right and perhaps an obligation to be informed. Robert Handy served as the first Board Chairman, then functioned as the Council’s Executive Director. In 1984, when Handy resigned his administrative role with the Council to assume the position of Executive Director of the Houston World Trade Association, the Council had hundreds of members with chapters in Houston, Clear Lake, Lake Jackson and Galveston.
In 1984, the organization’s name changed to Gulf Coast World Affairs Council, and leadership moved to the Center for International Studies at the University of St. Thomas in Houston. The Center’s Director William J. Cunningham, assumed the role of Executive Director of the Council.
During 1987-1988, the organization’s name changed again to Houston World Affairs Council. Later, these steps led to formation of the World Affairs Council of Houston, an organization still active and working to promote effective communication in a global community.
Records in this collection reflect the formative years of an organization devoted to promoting global understanding among local citizens, designing educational experiences locally as well as abroad, and creating opportunities for exchange of information in an international contexts.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Genre/Form of Material:
Brochures; Correspondence; Fliers (printed matter); Photographs; Posters
Topical Term:
Cultural relations; Diplomacy; Human rights; International relations; Political science
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Scope and Contents
Collection includes records relating to the formation and development of the Gulf Coast Council on Foreign Affairs and its successor organizations, the Gulf Coast World Affairs Council, and the Houston World Affairs Council. Documents reveal the administrative processes by which the organizations were governed and the various programs and events sponsored by the organizations. Such events include an array of invited speakers, some of considerable note, and trips to various countries, designed to facilitate international understanding and cross cultural experiences.
Collection arrangement follows the trajectory of the three sequentially evolving organizations. Materials generally follow chronological order within sub-series such as Administration, Business Activities, Correspondence, Financial Records, Membership, Programs, and World Affairs Press Coverage.
Detailed List of Contents
- Gulf Coast Council on Foreign Affairs (GCCFA), 1976-1984
  - Administration – History and Mission (GCCFA)
    - By-laws, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - By-laws, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - By-laws, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Organization Structure and Function, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Board of Directors (GCCFA)
    - Advisory Committee – Chapter Policy Enactment, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Executive Officer – Correspondence, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Executive Committee – Minutes, Correspondence, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Executive Committee – Minutes, Correspondence, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Executive Committee – Minutes, Correspondence, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Minutes, Correspondence, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Minutes, Correspondence, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Minutes, Correspondence, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Minutes, Correspondence, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
    - Minutes, Correspondence, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Minutes, Correspondence, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 16-17)
    - Minutes, Correspondence, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 18-19)
    - Minutes, Correspondence, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Minutes, Correspondence, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Meeting Places, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Business Activities (GCCFA)
    - Plans and Projects, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Plans and Projects, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Plans and Projects, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Plans and Projects, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Plans and Projects, 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence (GCCFA)
    - Marguerite Claghorn – Co-Chair GCCFA, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Alex Pratt – College of the Mainland, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Independent Contractor, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Jiri Kostelecky – Visiting Professor, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Advisory Committee Workshop, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Dr. Thomas M. Stauffer – Chancellor UH Clear Lake, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Kim Talley – Caribbean Horizons, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence returned by CEO’s to Join Council, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Executive Director Applicants, Foreign Service Officer Program, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Financial Records – Fundraising (GCCFA)
    - Funding Proposal – Organization Expansion, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Funding Proposal Follow-Up Correspondence, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Moody Foundation (Grant Proposal and Application), 1982 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Organization Structure and Function, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - K-12 Global Perspective Diffusion Proposal, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Proposal: Labor Industrial/Galveston County Development Councils, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Texas Committee for the Humanities, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Grant Application, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Financial Records – Report / Statements (GCCFA)
    - Great Decisions / Commager Finances, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Dues Account, 1976-1978 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Statement for Secretarial Work, 1976-1983 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Financial Statement, 1980-1981 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Finance Committee, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Benjamin Feld Donations, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Income and Expense Summary, 1982-1984 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Budget, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Financial Report, 1978-1980 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Financial Report, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Financial Report, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Financial Report, January-August 1982 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Financial Report, September 1982 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Financial Report, December 1982 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Financial Report, January-August 1983 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Financial Report, September-December 1983 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Financial Report, January-April 1984 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Beaumont Chapter (GCCFA)
    - Plans and Projects, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Galveston Chapter (GCCFA)
    - Plans and Projects, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Houston Chapter (GCCFA)
    - Annual Report, 1977-1980 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Plans and Projects, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Plans and Projects, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Plans and Projects, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence – University of St. Thomas, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Brochures, Committee Training, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Great Decisions Programs and Material, 1982-1984 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Program Announcements and Material, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Program Announcements and Material, 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Programs and Meetings, 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Executive Committee – Minutes, Correspondence, 1982-1983 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Executive Officers – Correspondence, 1982-1983 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Minutes, Correspondence, 1981-1982 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Minutes, Correspondence, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Minutes, Correspondence, 1984-1985 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Membership (GCCFA)
    - Board of Directors’ Resignations, 1977-1984 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Mailing List, 1978-1979 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Mailing List, 1980-1983 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Mailing List and Bulk Rates, 1984-1985 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Recruitment Correspondence, 1979-1984 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - International Business Directory and Committee, 1980-1981 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Members / Contacts and Material, 1982-1983 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Job Descriptions, Membership Applications, 1982-1983 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Board of Directors Election Material, 1984-1985 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Programs (GCCFA)
    - Houston Foreign Policy Conference on the Middle East, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - King TUT Tour, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Las Vegas, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Washington Tour, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Global Awareness in Service Project, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - European Community’s Visitor Program, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Burkitt Foundation, October 12, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Development Proposal – United Nations Association of the United States of America, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Nuclear Conference, 1982-1984 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - China Trip – Itinerary File, Geographers Tour, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - China Trip – Schwartz, Lawyers and Legislators, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - International Student Assembly, 1982-1983 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - College Consortium for International Studies, 1982-1983 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Benelux Study Tour, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Bingo, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Malcolm Barnebey, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Washington in the Spring, 1981-1983 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Washington in the Spring Photos, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Vatican, 1983-1984 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Education 5300, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Meoin Trip Study Program – Italy, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Rome Trip Recruiters, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Great Decisions, 1981-1985 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Five-Thirty Briefing, 1982-1985 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Brochures and Announcements, 1979-1985 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - News Releases and Material, 1976-1981 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - News Releases and Material, 1982-1983 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - News Releases and Material, 1984-1985 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Press Coverage (GCCFA)
    - Houston Area Media Guide, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Publications (GCCFA)
    - Houston Nuclear Conference, November 6-8, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Council Connection – A Publication by the Gulf Coast Council on Foreign Affairs, 1982-1983 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Council Connection – A Publication by the Gulf Coast Council on Foreign Affairs, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - World Affairs Press Coverage (GCCFA)
    - U.S.-China Friendship General Information, 1976-1979 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - International Issues, 1979, 1982, 1984-1985 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Photographs (GCCFA)
    - Photographs, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 29)
- Gulf Coast World Affairs Council (GCWAC), 1984-1987
  - Administration (GCWAC)
    - GCCFA Transition to GCWAC, Other Administrative Changes, 1984-1985 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Board of Directors (GCWAC)
    - Executive Committee – Minutes, Budget, 1983-1984 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Minutes, Correspondence, 1984-1985 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - List of Officers and Members of the Board, 1985-1986 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Business Activities (GCWAC)
    - Plans and Projects, 1985-1986 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence (GCWAC)
    - James W. Cater, 1985-1986 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - James W. Cater, 1986-1987 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Council for the Inter-American Security; Ann Kraulik Correspondence, 1985-1989 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Financial Records – Report / Statements (GCWAC)
    - Financial Reports, May-September 1984 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Bank Statements, 1986-1988 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Postage, Travel, and Labor Expenses; Cash Records, 1985-1988 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Telephone Expenses, 1985-1988 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Office and Council Expenses, 1986-1987 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Speaker Expenses, 1986-1988 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Membership Application Monies, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Houston Chapter (GCWAC)
    - Program Announcements and Materials, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Greats Decisions Programs and Material, 1985-1986 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Speaker, Foreign Policy Leadership Meeting, 1985-1986 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Minutes, Correspondence, 1985-1986 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Resignation Letters, 1985-1986 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Membership (GCWAC)
    - Mailing Lists, Information Questionnaire, 1984-1985 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Press Coverage (GCWAC)
    - Common Ground and Radio News, 1986-1988 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Programs (GCWAC)
    - Education Program for American Journalists – Alitalia Airlines, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Great Decisions, 1985-1987 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Publications (GCWAC)
    - Brochures and Other World Affairs Councils, 1984-1985 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - World Affairs Press Coverage (GCWAC)
    - International Issues, 1983-1985 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Houston World Affairs Council (HWAC), 1987-1988
  - Administration (HWAC)
    - GCWAC Transition to HWAC, 1987-1988 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Houston World Trade Association, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Foreign Policy Association Annual Report, December 4, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Business Activities (HWAC)
    - Plans and Projects, 1988, 1994, 1996-1997 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Board of Directors (HWAC)
    - Ann Kraulik – Speaker Correspondence, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Board of Directors, 1985-1991 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Minutes, Correspondence, 1987-1989 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Minutes, Correspondence, 1990-1997 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Meeting: Eastern Europe, the Soviet Union and The U.S. Foreign Policy, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - National Council on World Affairs Council – Annual Meeting (Pacific Interests), 1993-1997 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence (HWAC)
    - Jesse James, 1989 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Calvin Jones, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - American Foreign Service Association – Bill Cunningham, 1995-1996 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - American Foreign Service Association, 1994-1995 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - American Foreign Service Association, 1995 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - American Foreign Service Association, 1996 (Box 7, Folder 22-24)
    - William J. Cunningham, 1993-1996 (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - William J. Cunningham, 1997-1998 (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Financial Records – Report/Statements (HWAC)
    - Accounts and Balance Sheets, 1986-1989 (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - Market Report, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Programs (HWAC)
    - Dr. Peter Bechtold – The Making of U.S. Policy in the Middle East, 1987-1989 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Brian Fall – Grobachev, The Soviet Union, and the Western Response, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Paul Coetzee – Political Change in Southern Africa, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Yasou Hori – Japan in Transition, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - King Chen – Political Change in The Republic of China, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Great Decisions, 1988-1990 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Gerald Griffin – Overseas Recruitment, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Fredrich Hoess – ‘Perestroika’ and Change in Eastern Europe, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Gerald West – Investing in Developing Countries; Overlooked Opportunities, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - William E. Colby – Ethics in International Relations, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Program Announcements and Brochures, 1987-1990 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Program Announcements and Brochures, 1991-1998 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - John Garner, Charles Foster – Hong Kong Basic Law, 1990 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Donald Rice – Secretary of the Air Force, 1990-1992 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Dr. Mohamed Al-Mashat – U.S. Foreign Policy in the Middle East, 1990 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Rozanne Ridgeway – Uncertainties of Eastern Europe and the Unification, 1990 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Miguel Aleman Jr. – Mexican Ambassador, 1990 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Saudi Delegation Tours the U.S.A., 1990 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Dr. Georgi Arbatov – American Russian Relations, 1992 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Vladimir Lukin – Russian Ambassador, 1992 (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Ambassador Christopher Van Hollen – Middle East Update, 1993 (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - The Balkanization of the West: Trifkovic, Mestrovic, Sacirbey, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - The Balkanization of the West continued Correspondence, Faces of Sorrow, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - Zuberi Mwamba, PhD. – South Africa’s Elections: Hope and Challenge, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - Daiji Sadamori – A Vision of the 21st Century, and Shinzo Kobori – New U.S.-Japan Economic Agenda, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - Yukio Matsuyama – The Hosokawa Administration, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 26)
    - Lord Julian Amery of Lustleigh – Aftermath of the Cold War, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 27)
    - Joseph L. Nogee – Russia: The Continuing Crisis, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 28)
    - Lee-Suk Shin, PhD., Konstantin O. Sarkisov – Pacific Rim Security; Views from Russia and Korea, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 29)
    - Edward L. Peck – Selective Morality: The U.S. and other New World Order, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 30)
    - Jose Mario Pino – Ambassador of Argentina to U.S., 1994 (Box 8, Folder 31)
    - Program - News Release, 1995 (Box 8, Folder 32)
    - Texas Regional Workshop, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 33)
    - Leadership Houston, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 34)
    - Forum for International Policy, 1997 (Box 8, Folder 35)
  - Publications (HWAC)
    - 5 Year Plan (1993-1998) (Box 8, Folder 36)
    - Council Newsletter, 1995-2000 (Box 8, Folder 37)
  - World Affairs Press Coverage (HWAC)
    - U.S. Magazines, 1993-1997 (Box 8, Folder 38)
    - Asian Newsletters / Reports, 1993-1995 (Box 8, Folder 39)
    - Asian Newsletters / Reports, 1995-1997 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Asian Booklets, 1995-1997 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Asian Magazines, 1996-1997 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - News Clippings: The Americas, 1989, 1996-1998 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - News Clippings: Asia, 1996-1998 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - News Clippings: Europe / Russia, 1996-1998 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - News Clippings: Indo-Asia / Indonesia, 1996-1998 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - News Clippings: Middle East / Africa, 1995-1998 (Box 9, Folder 8)